<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.28 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC0819 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0819.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1034 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1035 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3986 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5891 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5891.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6761 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6761.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6762 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6762.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7706 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7706.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7595 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7595.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7686 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7686.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dnsop-alt-tld SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-alt-tld.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.lewis-domain-names SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.lewis-domain-names.xml">
]>


<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-hardie-resolution-contexts-01" category="info">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Resolution-Contexts-for-Internet-Names">Considerations for establishing resolution contexts for Internet Names</title>

    <author initials="T." surname="Hardie" fullname="Ted Hardie">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <email>ted.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2016" month="January" day="28"/>

    
    
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>This document examines the question of how to signal the appropriate resolution context for Internet names.  It starts from the premise that the Domain Name System is by far the most common resolution context but that it is not the only extant or potential resolution context for Internet names.</t>



    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>The history in <xref target="I-D.lewis-domain-names"/> and the usage in <xref target="RFC3986"/> both suggest that names registered in the domain name system are part of a larger set of Internet names.   If we model the system of Internet names as a set of directed graphs in an absolute naming context, following RFC 819 <xref target="RFC0819"/>, an Internet name is not necessarily a name in the domain name system, but is simply a unique name associated with that particular directed graph.  The resolution of the name, in other words, is independent from it being an “Internet name”.  The DNS is a common, but not the only, resolution context for Internet names.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="resolution-contexts" title="Resolution Contexts">

<t>The Domain Name System <xref target="RFC1034"/><xref target="RFC1035"/> provides the most common resolution system for Internet names by many orders of magnitude.  It has not, however, met all resolution requirements.  Multicast DNS <xref target="RFC6762"/> uses an alternative resolution service, as does TOR <xref target="TOR"/>.  Tor’s .onion names, in particular, appear to be effectively Internet names within a globally shared naming context; they simply happen to use an alternative resolution method. It seems likely that this is because of a wish to use protocols defined for DNS names as if they were defined for their non-DNS Internet names.  The .onion example was driven at least in part, in other words, because its users wanted https://identifier.onion/ to work as a signal that the resource was a web site, even if dereferencing the authority section did not use the DNS.  In order to share the HTTPS URI context, they needed to minimize the changes to the form of the URI.  That meant using https:// with a resolution trigger, rather than changing the URI (tor-https://, for example).</t>

<t>The key practical question that follows from the existence of alternative resolution contexts for a globally shared naming context is how you can determine what resolution context is associated with a particular Internet name.  In particular, it is important to determine whether it is part of the Domain name set of Internet names.  The de facto signal in use now is the top-most label of the Internet name.  If that label is within the known set of DNS top-most labels, we have a definite yes.  If it is within an established set of non-DNS top-most labels, we have a definite no. 
There are at least two unfortunate sets of potentially conflicting cases, where people are using labels with the intent to use this signal but have not risen to the level of “established no”.  In the first case, their usage may be mistaken for non-fully qualified names within the domain name system, resulting in the construction of a new Internet name where one was not intended (e.g. www.sld.allium becoming www.sld.allium.corp.example.com, rather than .allium being used as signal that this Internet name is not within the set of domain names).  The second case, which may overlap, is one in which the growth of the set of names in domain name system causes overlap (a new gTLD like .allium being assigned would conflict with the attempted use of .allium as a resolution context signal).  The risks of the two conflicting cases are pretty obvious, but despite that the use of a pseudo-TLD signal seems desirable to many setting up alternative resolution contexts.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="available-alternatives" title="Available Alternatives">

<t>There are many potential ways to signal that an Internet name is not within the DNS context, but a only subset of those ways allow for those names to be used in protocol contexts which currently expect DNS-based names.  A non-exhaustive list is set out below.  It is important to recognize that any Internet name designed to be used in such a context must accept limitations to achieve it.  Some of those limitations are syntactic, but the most important is that it must be a unique name within a directed graph within the overall Internet namespace.</t>

<t>Given that restriction, the universe of possible resolution context signals seems to be limited.  One option is using a designated sub-tree of the Internet namespace for non-DNS resolutions, with labels within the tree indicating which resolution context is meant. <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-alt-tld"/> describes one specific approach to this option.  While the use of this sub-tree may be esthetically less pleasing than a pseudo-TLD, it avoids the ambiguities which may arise during the development of alternative resolution context.</t>

<t>A second alternative is to fix either the set of top-level domains or the number of resolution contexts, so that ambiguity cannot occur.  While a fixed set of top-level domains might have seemed practical when the number of TLDs was limited to country codes and a strictly limited set of generic top-level domains, this has ceased to be a practical alternative.  Similarly, the creation of alternative resolution contexts cannot be effectively stifled, even were this desirable; those interested can implement and deploy them without registration of any kind.  That these may not interoperate or conflict with other deployments is, of course, a risk.</t>

<t>A third alternative within the DNS context is to continue the current registration of pseudo-TLDs and accept the consequences of ambiguity.  This will mean that conflicts between resolution context pseudo-TLDs and potential future TLDs must be managed and that the operational impact must be addressed.   A focus on deployment of mitigation strategies may reduce the operational consequences.  As an example, the deployment of loopback root zones <xref target="RFC7706"/> will reduce the impact of queries for pseudo-TLDs leaking to the root DNS name servers.  Similarly, policies for names registered as pseudo-TLDs may also limit potential conflict.</t>

<t>An alternative to signals within the DNS is making alternative signals easier.  URI registrations have gotten significantly easier<xref target="RFC7595"/> over time, but it might be possible to lower the bar further by creating a convention for using alternative resolution contexts.</t>

<t>As an example, we could set aside a string delimiter for this purpose as we set aside xn– to single out the ACE encoding for Internationalized Domain Names <xref target="RFC5891"/>.  That string delimiter could then be used to construct faceted URI schemes, one aspect of which contained the usual protocol indicator and the other the resolution context.  The ABNF for scheme is:</t>

<t>scheme      = ALPHA *( ALPHA / DIGIT / “+” / “-“ / “.” )</t>

<t>Setting aside a string delimiter such as +.+ would allow something like https://identifier.onion/ to become https+._tor//identifier/.  This would require updates to URI parsing libraries that intended to handle alternative resolution contexts, but the use of a common delimiter would lower the amount of code needed both to identify the core protocol and the alternative resolution contexts.  It might remain esthetically less pleasing, however, and it would prevent the use of IDNA-permitted characters as resolution context identifiers, something which the DNS-based solutions do allow.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="scope-considerations" title="Scope considerations">

<t>While this problem clearly has a potentially serious impact on both the scope of the relevant namespaces and on the code complexity required to deal with them, it is important to note that there are many Internet scale namespaces which do not present this problem.  An illustrative example may be taken from the instant messaging systems like WhatsApp.  As a mobile application, it confirms identity using E.164 numbers (by sending an SMS to the submitted number) and represents other users using the strings present in each phone’s contact list, so it does not need to maintain a globally unique presentation form for its users.  While it may use the DNS for resolution of its servers, it clearly could avoid that indirection by distributing resolution hints pointing to anycast servers, much as the DNS root does.  Within an app context, in other words, namespaces completely independent of each other and the DNS can reach Internet scale.  These may, like Twitter handles, overlap the Internet namespace when used from browser contexts.  @ExampleName may be clear within a Twitter app context,but ExampleName@twitter.com is commonly used outside it. Some context marker is required to avoid ambiguity and the potential for fishing, as ExampleName may be one individual in the twitter context and a different one in Facebook’s, but that context marker need not be the DNS.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="conclusions" title="Conclusions">

<t>There are clearly trade-offs among the available alternatives, as each has its own drawbacks as an indicator of resolution context.  Given, however, that the existence of multiple signals could generate even further interoperability issues and operational concerns, the creation of multiple signals is undesirable.  Any system which allows Internet names from alternate resolution contexts to be used in common protocol systems can likely be made to work, provided its drawbacks are accounted for and mitigated appropriately.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<t>This document describes a number of potential method for establishing a resolution context for an Internet name.   Should the resolution context to be used with a name not be sufficiently clear, it may be possible to provide alternative information in a different context.  That alternative information could provide an avenue for an attacker to stand up services which would mimic those present elsewhere, allowing the attacker to subvert the connection, steal credentials,</t>

</section>
<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This document currently has no actions for IANA.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">

<t>Thanks to Ed Lewis, Suzanne Wolff, and Andrew Sullivan for conversations leading up to this document; all errors of fact and judgement are, however, the author’s.</t>

</section>


  </middle>

  <back>


    <references title='Informative References'>

<reference anchor="TOR" target="https://www.torproject.org/">
  <front>
    <title>Tor</title>
    <author >
      <organization>The Tor Project</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2013"/>
  </front>
</reference>
&RFC0819;
&RFC1034;
&RFC1035;
&RFC3986;
&RFC5891;
&RFC6761;
&RFC6762;
&RFC7706;
&RFC7595;
&RFC7686;
&I-D.ietf-dnsop-alt-tld;
&I-D.lewis-domain-names;


    </references>



  </back>
</rfc>

